<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A friendly letter to Father Petre, concerning his part in the late King's government published for his defence and justification.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5400</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12138782</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12138782</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54828</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40496)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54828)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 596:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A friendly letter to Father Petre, concerning his part in the late King's government published for his defence and justification.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Political satire on Catholics and on Father Edward Petre, confessor of James II.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Petre, Edward, 1631-1699.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Anecdotes</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54828:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Friendly Letter TO <hi>Father Petre.</hi> Concerning his Part in the Late KING's GOVERNMENT.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for his Defence and Juſtification.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licens'd,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>
                              <hi>May</hi> 3. 1690.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. Fraſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Baily.</hi> MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:54828:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54828:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Friendly Letter to</hi> FATHER PETRE, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Father,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving ſome particular Obligation to you more than every body knows, I thought my ſelf obliged in point of Gratitude (which goes a great way in my Religion, though it is nothing in yours) to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make you ſome kind of Requital; and not knowing now where to find you, or any of your Friends, I was at a great loſs how to diſcharge my ſelf of that Debt: At laſt I conſidered, that to do you a real piece of Service behind your Back, were much better than an empty Thanks to your Face; and I knew of no greater Service I could do you, than to vindicate your Reputation to the World; and to ſhew that you have always acted like an honeſt Man; that is, one that is true and conſtant to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples he Believes and Profeſſes, which I take to be a good definition of an Honeſt Man. And this I do not at all fear to demonſtrate to your greateſt Enemies.</p>
            <p>As a farther proof of my deſire to ſerve you, I will likewiſe make bold to offer your Reverence ſome Advice, which if ever it has the luck to reach you, and you have the Wiſdom and Honeſty to follow it, I will preſume to ſay, ſhall eſtabliſh your Reputation to all future Ages. And in doing you theſe two pieces of Service, I hope I ſhall fully diſcharge what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54828:3"/> Obligation I have to you, and ſufficiently ſhew my ſelf your Friend.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, How comes your Reputation to need a Vindication? Sir, I muſt deal plainly with you, and tell you, That I can go no where, but I find every one blaming the ſtrange miſcarriages of the late King <hi>James;</hi> and the wiſer ſort that knew that Prince well, and how wholly devoted and given up he was to the <hi>Roman Catholic</hi> Religion, ſay, That it is impoſſible he ſhould have gon on in ſuch courſes, without the permiſſion at leaſt, or rather the direction of his Spiritual Guide, which you had favour to be: So that whatſoever wrong courſe the late King fell into, and perſiſted in, you are to Anſwer for it, to whoſe Guidance, there is no doubt, he wholly reſigned himſelf; and truly this, you and I, and all the World muſt grant.</p>
            <p>But for your Vindication, I will ſhew that in adviſing and encouraging the late King, in all theſe things the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks call Miſcarriages, you acted moſt agreeable to your Principles, that is, the true Principles of a <hi>Roman Catholic Guide,</hi> of the Order of the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> and therefore cannot (I think) but be confeſſed to be an honeſt man. We will then deſcend to Particulars of what is laid to the late King's Charge, and neceſſarily lights upon you, the Guide of ſo devoted a Prince's Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Hereticks ſay, That it is without Example, and beyond any ingenuous man's Imagination, that a Noble and an High-born Prince ſhould for many years make it his Glory to have his Word eſteemed moſt Sacred, and raiſe men to the higheſt Truſt and Confidence in it; ſo that men were ready to Blaſpheme when they talked of this ſubject, and to compare his Word to the Word of God, and ſay, <hi>That Heaven and Earth could ſooner paſs away than his Word fail.</hi> And when he had raiſed men to the higheſt confidence in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54828:3"/> it, with the greateſt ſolemnity to give this Sacred Word to his People, firſt in his Privy Council, and afterwards in full Parliament; and to bind it with the higheſt Solemnity in his Coronation-Oath, That he would invioably preſerve to 'em what they accounted moſt dear; that is, the Laws of the Land, and their Religion eſtabliſhed by Law: And yet that this Prince aſſoon as he was warm, and (as he thought) ſafe in his Throne, ſhould without any regard to Honour, without any fear of God, or ſhame of Man, ſo openly and apparently break this Sacred Word; this (they ſay) is to do all that lies in a man's power to deſtroy all Truſt and Confidence amongſt Men, and to put an end to humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. Now, that he did break this Sacred Word in the face of the Sun, and in the ſight of all Men, no Man can be ſo ſenceleſs to deny, that can but remember what was done with the Law of the <hi>Teſt,</hi> that Bulwark of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Safety, how it was wholly taken away by a total Diſpenſation, and that with a bare-faced deſign to bring in Popery, by making Popiſh Officers Maſters of thoſe they call Hereticks Lives and Fortunes, which miſchief that Law was only intended to prevent. 'Tis true, a Law may be diſpenced with in ſome particular caſes, where a thing is contrary to the Letter, but not to the meaning of the Law, becauſe the Intent and Meaning of a Law, is the Law: But totally to diſpence with a Law, againſt the plain and whole Intent and Meaning of it, is certainly to render the making of Laws Ridiculous and Uſeleſs, and to diſſolve the Conſtitution of the Government.</p>
            <p>Then for preſerving the Church of <hi>England</hi> according to his two ſolemn Promiſes in Council and Parliament; and indeed his Promiſes an hundred times over to particular Perſons; Did He not (ſay they) take the right courſe to preſerve the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in ſetting up the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54828:4"/> Commiſſion, to call in queſtion any that maintain'd the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> againſt growing Popery, which was Propagated, Cheriſh'd, and made to Grow, as much as 'twas poſſible in our cold and ſtubborn Climate, on purpoſe to ſupplant and thruſt out the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Did He not (ſay they) keep to his Word to defend and preſerve the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when as faſt as the leſſer Epiſcopal Sees became vacant, (for the good were kept for <hi>Original Catholicks</hi>) he fill'd them up with ſuch ſpecial Fellows, the very Scum and Dregs of all the Clergy, on purpoſe to make the Name of Proteſtant Biſhops ſtink and be abhorr'd, and to have fit Tools where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to Abuſe, Oppreſs, Suſpend, and Deprive all the honeſt Clergy; over whom he ſet theſe Beaſts, whoſe Filth and ill Manners prophan'd the very Name of Biſhops? Did He not (ſay they) begin finely to preſerve the Church of <hi>England</hi> according to his Promiſe, when he took care to poiſon the very Fountains, and planted one of the beſt Colleges in <hi>Oxford</hi> with Jeſuits? This and the like ſtuff, the Hereticks make a great noiſe with; and ſay, Was not Father <hi>Petre</hi> an accurſed Villain, to perſwade and thruſt on the poor Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotted Prince, to do things ſo manifeſtly contrary to his ſolemn and ſo often-repeated Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>But methinks, I ſee you and your Brethren ready to burſt your fides with laughing, when you hear all this diſmal Charge (as Hereticks think it) againſt you: And ſo truly would any Man laugh heartily, that underſtood any thing of Catholick Principles, to hear Men make ſuch a Buſineſs of a true Catholick's not keeping his Word with Hereticks: Alas? has not a whole Council declared, That Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks; and themſelves put in practice, what they had ſo determined with an infallible Spirit, by burning <hi>John Huſs,</hi> to whom they had given their Promiſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54828:4"/> for ſafe Conduct? And, indeed, is it not againſt common ſenſe, that a Man ſhould devote and vow himſelf to a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that declares nothing leſs than Deſtruction to all that oppoſe it; and yet ſhould be bound by his Promiſe, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Enemies of that Religion? Is not his Obligation to his Religion, greater than any other Obligation he can lie under? Therefore ſuch a Promiſe (as long as a Man is a true Roman Catholick) is Nonſenſe, is a Contradiction, and utterly Unlawful, or rather Impoſſible to be kept: It is as if a Man ſhou'd ſay, I will do that for you, which I cannot do. So that in making King <hi>James</hi> break this his Word with the Hereticks, Father <hi>Petre</hi> did no more than what he was bound to do, as a true Roman Catholick, and much more as one of the Order of the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> which not only is under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Obligation of all other Papiſts, but was founded with this particular Deſign, for the Deſtruction of Proteſtant Hereſie.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay, Why was there uſed ſo much poor Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation before-hand, to make Men believe and become ſo confident, That the late King was a Man that could and would keep his Word? Diſſimulation is mean in any Man, but much more in a great Prince. To this we anſwer, Are not true Catholicks to uſe the Cunning of the Serpent againſt Hereticks; the Spawn of the Serpent? And if true Catholicks are bound by their Religion to deſtroy Hereticks, (as moſt certainly they are) Are they not to uſe the means to do it? And can there be any ſafer or ſurer Means than by deceiving them? And if it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and commendable to deceive them once, (as the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> has declared) Is it not much more commendable to deceive them often, by a long train of Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation? This Accuſation then is wholly blown off from you, good Father <hi>Petre;</hi> and you appear to be a true Roman
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54828:5"/> Catholick Guide, of the Order of the Jeſuits; and the late King a true Son of the Roman Catholick Church, and a true Diſciple of your Order; all the Merits of which, he well deſerves to partake of: You both acted according to the Principles you profeſs, and therefore muſt be acknowledged to have acted honeſtly.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Objection is Ingratitude: A heavy Charge! The Hereticks ſay, That it is well known, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> had always ſtood firm to the Royal Family, and particularly had preſerved the late King from Ruine; had kept off the Stroke of the Laws from him; had ſaved him from being cut off by the Bill of Excluſion; had ſo often ventured their Lives and Fortunes for him, and thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eurr'd much Hatred, Reproach, and Slander, being conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually call'd Papiſts, or Papiſts in maſquerade for their pains: How then (ſay they) was it poſſible, that a Prince, ſo much Obliged by a People, as never Prince was more, ſhould as ſoon as they had ſetled him on the Throne, turn ſo bitter an Enemy to the Church of <hi>England</hi>-Men above all others? For ſo he often declared, That <hi>he looked upon them as his worſt Enemies.</hi> How is it poſſible to be believ'd, (ſay they) that he ſhould caſt all theſe off, with a <hi>Get you gone, you are not to be Truſted;</hi> and receive into his Boſom a SETT of new Friends, the very worſt of all the Diſſenters, Men of no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt or Reputation, and declared Enemies not only to him, but all his Family, and (which one would ſtand amaz'd at) whom ſo lately before he himſelf had unſpeakably diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd, by hanging up their Friends in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> in ſuch num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as plainly ſhews, that at that time he thought of nothing elſe but deſtroying all that ſort of Men? Now that he ſhould make them his Favourites, and treat them as if they were really ſuch, (though he hated them now as much as ever he did) only that he might have their help to deſtroy their old
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54828:5"/> Friends, whom he knew they hated for being ſo, and would be glad to deſtroy for that Reaſon; this was Ingratitude with a Witneſs: And this amongſt Hereticks looks like a heavy Charge; but indeed how light is it to any Man, that underſtands any thing of Roman Catholick Principles? Is not a true Catholick's Obligation to Holy Church, much greater than his Obligation to particular Perſons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpecially to Hereticks? Or indeed, can a true Roman Catholick have any Obligation to any Man that is an Enemy to his Religion? The late King's Religion was the deareſt thing to him in the World; and the promoting of it he eſteem'd his greateſt Glory: He then that oppos'd his Religion, and put a ſtop to the acquiring of his deſired and darling Glory of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an heretical Nation, and ſaving a Succeſſion of Souls to the Worlds end, ought certainly to be accounted his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Enemy. And did ever any Man oppoſe this glorious Deſign like the Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Men? Did not their Nobility and Gentry univerſally ſhew their ſtubborn averſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and throw up their honourable and profitable Places, rather than they would let the leaſt thing paſs, that might help on the glorious Work? Were not thoſe Heads of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, the Biſhops, ſo obſtinate, that they choſe to go to a Priſon, rather than to make the leaſt ſtep towards a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance? And did not the Clergy in general venture to loſe their Livings, and to beg with their Wives and Children, rather than they would read the King's Declaration? On the other hand, Did not ſome Diſſenters comply to the taking off the Teſt and Penal Laws? Accept Diſpenſations, and ſubmit to the Regulation of Corporations? Make flattering and fulſome Addreſſers enough to compile a new Academy of Compliments? And ſuppoſing they had done none of all this, (as ſome of them ſcorn'd it) Yet is not divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Hereticks the way to deſtroy them? And did not the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54828:6"/> cheriſhing of Diſſenters promote Diviſion? So that that was the only means that cou'd be thought of, for pulling down the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is the main, or rather the only Stay of the Northern Hereſie, that which gives it all its Strength, Beauty, and Reputation. What though ſome Men the late King encourag'd and careſs'd, had a hand in killing his Father; and others of them had petition'd for his Blood? Yet if the cheriſhing of them was neceſſary to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Good of the Roman Church, was he to neglect that, for which all his Preachers told him he was rais'd to the Throne, and preſerv'd divers times by Miracle, and ſo be ungrateful to his GOD, to be grateful to Men, nay, to Hereticks? Was he not bound to lay aſide all humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, either of Love or Hatted, for the ſake of this bleſſed Deſign? The late King then had ſo little cauſe to be aſham'd of ſuch a Forgetfulneſs, both of Benefits and Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for the ſake of Holy Church, that 'tis indeed no ſmall Glory to him, that he was able to overcome all Humanity and ſenſe of Gratitude to Mankind, with a far more predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant ſenſe of Love and Duty to his dear Mother the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church: And had he not great and glorious Examples of Catholick Princes that did the ſame before him? That out of Zeal to their Religion, utterly forgot all humane Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations? Did the <hi>Suffolk</hi>-Men's bringing Queen <hi>Mary</hi> to Crown, ſo oblige her that ſhe could not burn them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards for being Hereticks? And does not the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King now upon the Earth, kill, torment, beggar, or baniſh all the Proteſtants of his Realm, to whom he was beholden for his Kingdom?</p>
            <p>Tis plain then, that the higheſt Ingratitude in a Roman Catholick Prince, is highly praiſe-worthy, when the fooliſh Humanity of Gratitude does oppoſe the holy Deſign of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Rom. Cath. Religion. If then (good Father) you,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54828:6"/> or any of your Society, did perſwade your <hi>Devoto</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn ſuch fooliſh and ſinful Reſpects, you did but like true Roman Catholick Guides, and deſerve to be approved as Honeſt Men, that acted according to their Principles.</p>
            <p>3. But again the Hereticks ſay, Though what is Decent or Humane hath no force with a true Zealot of the Roman Catholick Religion, yet one would think natural affection to Children ſhou'd bear ſome ſway in all men's Hearts, and ſhou'd be very difficult to be rooted out: to diſ-inherit ones own Fleſh and Blood, to cut off ones own Poſterity for all future Ages, from enjoying thoſe Priviledges they were born to, hath ſomething in it ſo unnatural, ſo monſtrous, that it aſtoniſhes. And men that find nothing in themſelves that wou'd incline them to any ſuch thing, can hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; and ſome good natur'd Hereticks are apt to ſay, That ſure the buſineſs of the P—of <hi>W</hi>—cou'd not be a Cheat; but then (ſay they) it was an unpardonable Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in you, to let a Reality look ſo like a Cheat; if you had a real Child to be born, Why wou'd you let it be born uuder ſo terrible a diſadvantage? Why wou'd you let ſo great and irrepairable an injury be done to the poor Child, and all his Poſterity (if ever he ſhou'd come to have any) as not to let him be born with the cleareſt Evidence? And what Evidence was like the taking all poſſible care that the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> (who was ſo nearly concern'd) ſhou'd have certainly been at the Birth, inſtead of taking care that She ſhou'd be an hundred Miles off at that time? And why was not the then Princeſs of <hi>O</hi>—ſent to, that ſhe alſo might have been at the Labour; Or at leaſt, that She might have deputed ſome Ladies of her own chuſing, to have been preſent for her own Satisfaction? What (ſay the Hereticks) were not theſe Great Princeſſes concern'd in the matter? Who were like to be put by the Succeſſion of Three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54828:7"/> by this means? And who were likely to doubt, and to diſpute it, and to have all the Hereticks in the Three Nations, and every where elſe on their ſide? Were not they by all means to have had full and clear ſatisfaction given them, if there had been any Fatherly-Love amongſt you to your Princely Babe? A man that had but a ſmall Eſtate to leave to a Son, wou'd take care that the next Heir ſhou'd be fully ſatisfied of the true Birth of his Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſpecially if there had been any doubtful Speeches as if there was a Cheat intended, as you know it was in every Bodies Mouth, that the late Q. <hi>Mary</hi> had but a feigned great Belly; and if a Man wou'd take care to leave his Son a clear Title to a ſmall Eſtate, Is it credible that you ſhou'd be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural to your Babe, as not to take care to leave him a clear Title to Three Kingdoms? You know the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> had the ſatisfaction given him, to ſee <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. come out of his Mothers Belly, though he <hi>knew not how the Devil he got in.</hi> And ſo much ſatisfaction you might have afforded one, or both of the two Princeſſes, if you had had any thing re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l to produce. To let your P—of <hi>W</hi>—then (if he was really ſuch) be Born under ſuch great Suſpitions, was a moſt inhumane Cruelty to the Babe, even like ſtifling him as ſoon as he was Born, or (which is worſe) condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him and all his Poſterity to continual Baniſhment, or violent Deaths. And what had the poor Infant done, to deſerve this from you? (if he was real) Did he not come to Eſtabliſh the Roman Catholick Cauſe for ever? And were you ſuch <hi>Dolts,</hi> as not to take care that ſuch a Child ſhou'd be Born with the fulleſt and cleareſt Evidence, ſuch as ſhou'd make him appear an undoubted Heir, even to the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Hereticks? Are you, or your Succeſſors, ever like to have ſuch a fair Advantage again to the Worlds end, as you have utterly loſt, by letting your Catholick Heir,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54828:7"/> (if he was true) be Born under ſo much Doubt and Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it was all one as if he had been a Cheat?</p>
            <p>Truly, I muſt confeſs, this ſtrikes home, and proves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerably, That either you were the greateſt Fools and Block-heads under the Sun, or that the buſineſs of the P. of <hi>W</hi>—was all a Cheat.</p>
            <p>But you are not unprovided (I know) with a ſufficient Anſwer to all this: I believe you cannot but ſmile with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation at theſe pretended Friends of yours, that wou'd excuſe what they think a great piece of Knavery, by charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you with ſuch notorious and palpable Folly. You thank them (I believe) kindly for their Love, but deſire none of their Complements; you wou'd not for the ſaving ſuch a loſt Game as the P. of <hi>W.</hi> venture the great Stake of Eſteem and Reputation that you have all over <hi>Europe</hi> for Politicians, by vertue of which you bear ſuch a ſway in ſo many great Princes Councils: you have been thought Knaves ſometimes, but were never before thought Fools, nor never deſire ſo to be thought; and therefore wou'd not have any wiſe Man once Imagine that the P. of <hi>W</hi>—was real, whereby you muſt ſtand ſenceleſs Block-heads upon Record, that were uncapable of underſtanding their Intereſt, and making their Advantage of it. But you deſire rather that all wiſe Men ſhou'd applaud your Wit, That having ſo great a Cheat to put upon a Nation, that was all along ſo Jealous of it, you did it ſo dextrouſly, that to this day the Cheat cannot be fully laid open; you are confident that none that know you right, will ever think it other than a Cheat, and yet all muſt confeſs you carried it cunningly.</p>
            <p>As for the former heavy Charge (as Hereticks think) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, of perſwading the poor Zealous Prince to do ſo unnatural a thing as to cut off his whole Poſterity, to ſet up a Suppoſititious Brood; this is very defenſible upon Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54828:8"/> Principles; for a good Catholick ought certainly to love <hi>Holy Church</hi> better than Father or Mother, Wife or Children. And did not the glorious Saint, Q. <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> endeavour to cut off her own Fleſh and Blood, her own Siſter, to ſet up <hi>Timothy Malt</hi> on the Throne of her Fathers? She wou'd have done as much, no doubt, by her own Daughters, if ſhe had had any, and they had been Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and ſtood in the way, as her Siſter did. She was as Unnatural as lay in her power for Holy Church: And this Trick had taken then, and in all likely-hood at this time the <hi>Malt's</hi> had been the Reigning Family, inſtead of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> had not K. <hi>Philip</hi> ſpoil'd the deſign; partly hoping when he had buried Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> he might marry that Siſter of hers, and ſo hold this Kingdom in her right; and partly fearing, that if his Son (by his firſt Wife) <hi>Don Carlos</hi> ſhould happen to Die, this young <hi>Malt</hi> ſhould carry away the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> from any Son that might be born to him afterwards, or from his Daughter the <hi>Infanta Iſabella.</hi> that was as good a Catholick as he. If K. <hi>Philip</hi> err'd in this, he made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for it afterwards; for when ſome Years after this, he came to underſtanding that his own Son, <hi>Don Carlos,</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to the <hi>Proteſtant Hereſie;</hi> in high Indignation at this, and Zeal for Holy Church, he threw off all natural affection at once to that his only Son; and not content to exclude him from the Succeſſion, he took a ſurer way to ſecure the Catholick Religion, by making him die in Priſon. This heroical Action of his, though he modeſtly repreſented it to the then Pope <hi>Pius</hi> V. in his Letter (which I doubt not your Fatherhood has read, in the Life of that Pope, now a Saint in your <hi>Kalendar,</hi> written by <hi>Girolamo Catena,</hi> the Secretary of his Favourite Nephew, and Printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> with a Dedication to Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> V.) yet his Holineſs ſet a juſt value upon it; and becauſe he cou'd go no higher for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54828:8"/> a Parallel, he reſembled it to God's giving his Son for the Redemption of Mankind; For, ſays your Hiſtorian, he preſently call'd a Conſiſtory, and there caus'd this Letter to be read; and then with Eyes and Hands lifted up to Heaven, he broke out into the Apoſtle's Words; <hi>He that ſpared not his only Son, but gave him up for us all; How ſhall he not with him,</hi> &amp;c. That which this great Saint and Head of the Church judged to be ſo highly Meritorious in King <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> was indeed a higher Inſtance by many degrees, of aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning natural Affection, than that was to which you perſwaded King <hi>James:</hi> But your Work was the eaſier, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially having to do with a Prince that would think it a very Scorn to be told that any Catholick King of them all, had a greater Zeal than he has for the Catholick Church: And for the neceſſity of it, that he ſhould find out ſome way or other, to diſinhereit that Heretical Daughter, whom he uſed to call by the Name of Queen <hi>Beſs,</hi> you need not tell him that ſhe was as likely to do as much Miſchief to the Church, as ever Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did; and therefore ſhe ought to be prevented, in the ſame manner as that Queen ſhould have been, if King <hi>Philip</hi> had not hindred it. For the doing of this, in that way of a Mock-Childbirth, you had ſuch a Queen to act it for you, as perhaps never was in the World; an <hi>Italian</hi> by Birth, that has the Blood of four or five Popes in her Veins; an adoptive Daughter of <hi>France,</hi> a moſt bigotted Diſciple of your Order; one that ſeem'd to have been ſent hither for ſuch a purpoſe, <hi>far 'un fioliolo,</hi> by all means to get a Son. I would not ſeem by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the Neceſſity of this, or the Advantages you had for the doing of it, with ſo much Eaſe, Cloſeneſs, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crefie, to derogate any thing from your Merit (good Father) in the Advice or Contrivance of any thing elſe that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly yours: For whatſoever that was, (as no doubt your Part
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54828:9"/> was very great in this whole Buſineſs, it cannot be denied that it was worthy of your Self and your Order, and moſt agreeable to the Principles of your Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The laſt Accuſation of the Hereticks againſt the late King, and conſequently againſt his Guides, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt You in particular, ſeems to me the greateſt; and truly it ſtrikes a Horrour into all Men's Spirits that think on it. They ſay, How could it be propos'd to reduce this heretical Land to the Roman Catholick Religion, without making it ſwim in Blood? Your Arguments never did much any where, but leaſt of all in <hi>England,</hi> where you have been ſo often foil'd by the Learned Men of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and where your Religion alſo is ſo much againſt the Intereſt of the Kingdom: Therefore it was obſerv'd by an old expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Miſſionary, that had ſtaid long in <hi>England,</hi> That this Nation was to be reduced to the Roman Catholick Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by nothing but the Sword. <hi>And</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>when the young Miſſionaries come firſt over, they think they can do mighty Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with their Arguments; but after they have been in</hi> England <hi>ſome time, they are all of my Opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, this is ſo known and received a Maxim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, That <hi>England</hi> is never to be converted but by the Sword: That the late King himſelf, in a Speech to the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> told them, That he knew the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of the Roman Catholick Religion into theſe Realms, muſt coſt ſo much Blood, and make ſuch a Deſolation, that he had the greateſt Horrour at it imaginable; and hop'd that none of them wou'd have ſuch hard Thoughts of him, as to believe him capable of ſo much Cruelty and Barbarity, (even as <hi>Hazael</hi> ſaid to the Prophet—) Well then, King <hi>James</hi> knew well enough what it would coſt, and what muſt be done to bring in Popery; and yet Popery he was reſolv'd to bring in, (as I am ſure every Man in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:54828:9"/> believed two years ſince; and every Man muſt believe, in ſpight of his Heart, that knows the Jeſuits his abſolute Guides.)</p>
            <p>What Excuſe then can be made for ſo great Cruelty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended? 'Tis the Buſineſs and End of a King, or Supreme Governour, to defend from Injury; to Preſerve and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the Lives and Fortunes of his Subjects: How then can any one be a King over thoſe he thinks himſelf bound, and reſolves to Deſtroy? There are ſome indeed ſo tender-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in themſelves, and of ſuch tender Underſtandings to boot, that they won't believe this; or at leaſt are afraid to be known they believe it: And therefore they ſay, Surely the late King did not Deſign to bring in Popery at all, or at leaſt not by ſuch rough ways: But by ſuch ways all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Catholicks conclude it muſt be brought in, or not at all.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion then is only, Whether the late King reſolv'd to bring in Popery; and if his Guides were not reſolv'd to bring it in by him. All Men muſt conclude them the moſt ridiculous People under the Sun, that they would ſuffer the late King to give ſo many apparent ſigns of his Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to bring it in, which were more than ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm a Nation, jealour before of ſuch a thing, in the aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Belief that he was reſolved to do it.</p>
            <p>In anſwer then to theſe Objections againſt Father <hi>Petre,</hi> and the Society, the Undoubted and Abſolute Guides of the late King's Conſcience: I ſay, That I believe that Father <hi>Petre</hi> and his Brethren will conn them little thanks, that go about thus to excuſe them, by making them ſuch notorious Sots, as to make ſuch an appearance of bringing in Popery, as made all People believe it, and put them in care how to eſcape the dreadful Conſequences of that Change: And yet that the Jeſuits ſhou'd never deſign any ſuch thing? They had
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54828:10"/> not, certainly, ſo mean an eſteem of the profitableneſs of having their <hi>Devoto</hi> poſſeſs'd of three ſuch Kingdoms, as to endanger his loſing them (only as the <hi>French</hi> expreſs it, <hi>De Guaiete de Coeur</hi>) for nothing. And I do very believe Father <hi>Petre</hi>) that neither you, nor any of your Brethren, wou'd for all the World be robb'd of the Glory of having made ſuch an Heroick Attempt to reduce theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms to the Roman Catholick Religion: And I dare ſwear for yonr <hi>Devoto,</hi> that he wou'd not accept of theſe three Kingdoms again, if he were fully ſatisfied that it were utterly impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ever to make them Roman Catholicks; as he nobly ſaid to one of the Society, <hi>He had rather die the next day after this Land was made Roman Catholick, than Live and Reign fifty Years in Peace and Proſperity over Hereticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have then no need of your fooliſh Friend's Excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who wou'd make you as weak as themſelves, and rob you of that immortal Glory, (which you wou'd not loſe to ſave your Lives a thouſand times over) of having once boldly and roundly attempted to bring the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion into <hi>England.</hi> You are ready to avow this to all the World, and are proud of it; as indeed (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your Principles) you have reaſon to be. Neither, will you ſtick, among Friends, as ingenuouſly to confeſs, That it cou'd never have been brought in without horrible Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; which you can very well juſtifie upon Rom. Catholick Principles; and ſo ſtill maintain your Title of Honeſt Men.</p>
            <p>For herein you proceed according to the greateſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in your Church, which you ought always to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and never to diſpute. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> You have the Authority of divers Popes, that have almoſt continually exhorted Temporal Princes to uſe their Sword againſt Hereticks, particularly of <hi>Innocent</hi> III. who turn'd the whole <hi>Croiſade</hi> that was prepared againſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54828:10"/> the Infidels that poſſeſſed the Holy Land againſt the <hi>Albigeois:</hi> And of Pope <hi>Julius,</hi> who adviſed <hi>Charles</hi> V. not to trouble himſelf with Colloquies and Diſputes, but to uſe his Sword againſt the Hereticks to cut them off. And ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of your Councils have declared, That a Prince that does not uſe his utmoſt endeavour to deſtroy and root Hereticks out of his Dominion, ought to be depriv'd. And according to theſe great and infallible Authorities of the Roman Church, the trueſt and moſt zealous Roman Catholicks have in all Ages acted. So did <hi>Simon Montfort,</hi> and (as the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian ſays) 500000 Roman Catholicks with him, in a <hi>Croiſade</hi> againſt the Hereticks, Killing, Burning, and Deſtroying all they could find in <hi>Languedoc</hi> and the Places adjacent, 60000 Hereticks being but one Break-faſt for them. And what havock was made of them in ſucceeding <hi>Croiſades,</hi> Roman Catholick Hiſtorians ſufficiently declare.</p>
            <p>What has been done by Catholick Princes, eſpecially by the Dukes of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and by the moſt <hi>Chriſtian Kings,</hi> the eldeſt Sons of the Roman Church, whenever they were ſuch <hi>Rom. Cath.</hi> as they ought to be, the World is not ignorant. They have made whole Rivers of Heretick's Blood ſtream through their Countries: So did the glorious St. <hi>Charles</hi> IX. in the <hi>Paris</hi> Maſſacre: So would St. <hi>Garnet</hi> and his Accomplices have done here in <hi>England,</hi> and more too, if they had not been unluckily prevented in the great and pious Deſign of the Powder-Plot; for which he is painted in the College at <hi>Rome,</hi> with a Glory about his Head. What cheerful Bonfires did St. <hi>Mary,</hi> of ever bleſſed Memory, make of Hereticks in her Reign? And thus acted thoſe true Roman Catholicks in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and ſo indeed muſt every one that is a true Roman Catho, lick act, whenever he has opportunity; if he does not, he is falſe to his Principles, and not truly what he profeſſes to be.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54828:11"/>
            <p>And 'pray, What hurt in all this? Are not the Enemies of GOD and his Church to be deſtroyed? And do we not believe in our Conſciences all Hereticks to be ſuch? Nay, indeed, is it not a Kindneſs to ſtubborn Hereticks them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſpeedily to cut them off, that they may not increaſe their Sins, and conſequently their Damnation? That they may no longer impiouſly oppoſe Holy Church? That they may not Infect others with their Leproſie of Hereſie? And that they may not breed a Spawn of Hereticks, fit only to fry in Hell-fire.</p>
            <p>In deſigning then to bring in the Roman Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion into <hi>England;</hi> and in order to that, deſigning to kill all ſtubborn Hereticks that would not ſubmit to it, Father <hi>Petre</hi> and the Society did but what was the Duty of all true Roman Cotholicks; and according to their Principles, acted like right honeſt Men. There may ſeem indeed to lie ſome Objection againſt their Prudence, in the Management of this Deſign, in that they ſhewed their Deſign too ſoon, before they were ready to Complete it.</p>
            <p>To which it may very well be anſwered, That if the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be rightly conſidered, it will be found, that this was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed more their Misfortune than their Fault. The Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers ſay, That Nature makes every thing in Perfection, according to the Capacity of the Matter it works in: And we know the beſt Workman, if he has but bad Tools and croſs Stuff to work on, will make but indifferent Work. Let thoſe that blame the Management, conſider impartially, what they themſelves would or could have done in all their Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Theſe poor Men had been gaping for an Opportunity to bring in Popery near an hundred years; and when they had the faireſt opportunity that ever they had or hoped for, and the like to which they could never expect again, wou'd you
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54828:11"/> not have them make the beſt uſe they cou'd of this Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity? Was not King <hi>James</hi> thought by every one to be a Man on whoſe Life there was little dependence, and of whom it was unlikely there ſhould be any Catholick Heirs to live to ſucceed him? And did not the inſolent Hereticks threaten them every moment, what work they would make with them, if once he ſhould fail? So that their Lives, and what was much more dear to them, their great Deſign depended wholly upon the ſingle crazy Thread of the late King's Life. And did not theſe Men that had ſtood gaping ſo long, wait almoſt three Years, without plainly going about their Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? which was an Age to Men, whoſe Hearts were before ſo ſick of having their Hopes delayed. Then, indeed, when they thought it muſt be <hi>Now,</hi> or <hi>Never,</hi> (which was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Word among the Roman Catholicks about that time, and when they drank and wiſhed Courage and good Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to the Undertakers) they fell roundly to their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</p>
            <p>They had by their Arts before inflamed the two Parties of Church-men and Diſſenters, one againſt another; and they did not doubt but the Diſſenters wou'd effectually help them to pull down the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the greateſt Obſtacle to their deſigns? And who wou'd have thought they ſhould have been ſo much diſappointed of this hope? Then they uſed the craftieſt means, and greateſt diligence imaginable, to model a Parliament that might remove the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws</hi> out of the way, that their Friends might be capable of all places by Law; and then be ſure, none ſhould have had any Offices of Truſt; none ſhould have had power over the Lives and Eſtates of Hereticks, but ſuch as thought themſelves bound in Conſcience to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them: They new Modelled the Army as much as they cou'd; and brought in as many Foreigners as they cou'd,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54828:12"/> without danger of an immediate Rupture: And who would ever have thought, that an Army compos'd (as it was then) for the moſt part of Men, whoſe Fortune depended wholly on their Employment, would not have Fought, or done any thing for their Pay, without examining the Cauſe? Pray do but conſider, How many came over with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who had <hi>Proteſtant Swords,</hi> though they themſelves were <hi>Papiſts.</hi> No Man indeed, that had ever liv'd abroad (as all the Jeſuits had) and ſeen how little Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers mind the Cauſe they Fight for, cou'd ever have dream'd that the whole Deſign ſhou'd have been ſpoil'd by the Army that was to carry it on, and had been manag'd and modell'd almoſt four years together for that purpoſe. Well! I am ſure every body muſt grant, that the Jeſuites had at leaſt great probabilities to build upon the Army, when the Late King had made it his Buſineſs ſo much to oblige the Seamen, and Soldiers of Fortune in the Kingdom: And thus confiding in the Army, they had nothing elſe to fear, but might go on boldly, ſince they cou'd not apprehend any ſuddain Riſing of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Men (who were the main Body of the Kingdom) by reaſon of their habitual Loyalty; and from Diſſenters they hop'd they ſhou'd have no diſturbance, ſince they had ſo much car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs'd and oblig'd them, and made them the King's <hi>new Friends</hi> and Darlings: They therefore confidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, firſt to cleanſe the Nurſeries, the Univerſities from Heretical Plants, and to plant Catholicks in their ſtead; then they found out a way to remove all honeſt Church of <hi>England</hi> Men from their Churches, by commanding a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> to be read by all the Clergy; which if they did read, they were Betrayers of the Law of the Land, by giving ſuch an Approbation to an Illegal Diſpenſing Power; they had made themſelves ridiculous to the People,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54828:12"/> and ſinn'd againſt their own Conſciences; and had likewiſe given a fair opportunity to the Jeſuites of impoſing down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Popery upon them in the next place. And we know that all that wou'd not have been ſuch Knaves or Fools, were to have been deprived; and when the Biſhops had the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and the Courage to oppoſe this well-laid Project by their <hi>Petition,</hi> we know they flung them into the <hi>Tower, in Terrorem,</hi> and preſently brought forth the Babe, to ſhew People that the Deſign wou'd not die with King <hi>James,</hi> and that their hopes of any Relief by a Change were cut off. They had ſet up Popiſh Chappels in <hi>London, Oxford, Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol, &amp;c.</hi> which thing alone to be able to effect in <hi>England,</hi> was enough to make a Jeſuites Heart leap for joy, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him ſo, that he knew not where he was, nor cou'd think any thing impoſſible for him, that had brought things to paſs ſo much beyond his Expectation. Nay, they had got the Pope's <hi>Nuncio</hi> to be publickly Feaſted at the <hi>Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Hall</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> which was next door to an owning of the Pope's Authority in that Proteſtant City; they had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Four Roman Catholick Biſhops to take care of the Souls of all the Nation, inſtead of the Proteſtant Biſhops they caſt into the <hi>Tower;</hi> and they, to begin their Office, writ a moſt loving Paſtoral Letter to their whole Flock; the time being not yet come for Dragooning.</p>
            <p>Indeed, juſt as they were Sailing with full Sails to all their Deſires, unluckily comes the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> over, and ſtops the Bells; and all things turn'd upon a ſuddain, it wou'd even turn a Man's head to think how.</p>
            <p>Well; Men may blame this or that in Councils when they don't ſucceed, and every body can ſee Faults afterwards, when there is no helping them; but had any of thoſe that blame the Management been Jeſuites themſelves, they wou'd have done juſt as they did: There was danger in carrying
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54828:13"/> on things ſo faſt, and there was no leſs danger in delaying them; for though they had made a Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> yet if K. <hi>James</hi> ſhould have happened to have fail'd, their Prince muſt have been taken out of their Hands, and bred up by Proteſtants: A thing of ſo great horror to his Queen-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that when it was once mentioned to her, ſhe declar'd, <hi>She would rather kill him with her own hands.</hi> But this ſhe might have done with as little pain to her Bowels, as ſhe had in the Child-birth.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, there was danger on all hands, and no Man could divine where the greateſt lay: The Jeſuites did as much as Men cou'd do in their Circumſtances; they ſaw as much as Men cou'd ſee in the Light they were in, and they wrought as well as Men could work with the Tools they had, and on the Stuff they were to work on. If the deſign did not ſucceed, it is not the firſt well-laid Deſign that has miſcarried; and therefore it was truly more the Jeſuites Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune than their Fault; or perhaps the Sins of the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks hindred them from being knock'd on the Head, or Converted, they were not worthy of ſo great a Bleſſing: Howſoever, the good Fathers, and their <hi>Devoto,</hi> did all that lay in them to do them this kindneſs, and muſt have the Glory of heartily endeavouring it, though they did not effect it. They have all done like true Zealous Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, as they deſire to be thought, and would not loſe the Glory of the Zeal they have ſhewn for Holy Church for Ten Thouſand Kingdoms: So that no fault, either of Diſhoneſty or Imprudence, can be laid to their Charge, but rather they deſerve the Character of True and Zealous Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks. Only there is one little blemiſh indeed, that ſeems ſtill to ſtick upon their <hi>Devoto</hi> (and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Guide of his Conſcience) and to ſoil all his Glory, and to oppoſe his pretence to ſo much Heroick Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54828:13"/> and that is, his ſtill Indulging himſelf ſo much Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with Women: And that he ſhould take upon him to be an Apoſtle, to bring all other Chriſtians to his Sect; as if they could not be Saved otherwiſe than in his way, ſeems very ſtrange to them that do not underſtand your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but if they underſtood it, they would eaſily ſee how to Anſwer this little Objection. For Catholick Prieſts, and eſpecially thoſe of your Order (as appears in the Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Morals of the Jeſuites</hi>) have not quite the ſame O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of this Sin that Hereticks have: 'Tis a Sin that moſt Men, and they themſelves, often find ſo great a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion to from Nature, that they can hardly reſiſt it, therefore they judge of it favourably: And beſides, they do not think as Hereticks do, that nothing but the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt in thoſe that Repent and forſake it, can waſh it away; for they have the Merits of the Saints too, of whom the moſt perfect, even our Lady herſelf, according to their <hi>Legends,</hi> have often been very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious to ſuch kind of Sinners; and ſome of their Saints themſelves have been noted for ſuch Sins, and yet found them no Obſtacle to their Canonization.</p>
            <p>Again, Catholicks think there may be Satisfaction made by Men themſelves for their Sins: And if Men ſhew a great deal of Zeal for Holy Church, and deſtroy her Enemies the Hereticks, though they ſhould be a little faulty in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; yet according to the Opinion of Roman Catholick Writers, who have ever reported them great Saints, that were zealous for Holy Church, (though notoriouſly given to this and other Faults) ſuch ought ſtill to be accounted Saints, as appears in St. <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Tours,</hi> and other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And truly, without this Fault in Princes, oftentimes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54828:14"/> the Guides of their Conſciences can work but little good with them: For if they did not find them tardy in ſuch things, they could never prevail with them to make ſuch mighty Satisfactions; and to do ſo much good to Holy Church, in enriching Her, and deſtroying Her Enemies, and the like, to make amends for their Faults, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with Holy Mother-Church, to Mortgage the whole Treaſure of the Merits of the Saints, to purchaſe their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs.</p>
            <p>So that if this be a Fault in any Prince, it is the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo much Good, it affords ſo advantagious an Handle to the Guide of his Conſcience, ſo mightily to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit Holy Church, that it is a great Queſtion, fit to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted in their Scools, Whether a good Roman Catholick Guide of a Princes Conſcience, be bound wholly to root it out of him? If he be bound in Conſcience to do it, it is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pities; for it is certain, it is not for his Intereſt, or the Intereſt of the Church. And all Roman Catholicks agree, that he is bound to promote, as much as he can, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of his Church. Now their Schools hold, That in a Caſe of Conſcience, where there are Probabilities and Doctor's Opinions on both ſides, a Man may follow either ſide without Sin; and be ſure the Confeſſor will take the moſt profitable ſide. The Popiſh Guides therefore cannot but laugh at the Proteſtant Miniſters, who teach, that there is no Forgiveneſs of Sin, but upon Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and forſaking Sin; and ſo get nothing by the People's Sins, which have been the Enriching of the Romiſh Church.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:54828:14"/>
            <p>Thus have I (good Father) fully Juſtified You, and the reſt of the Society, as to your Honeſty and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in Acting according to True Roman Catholick Principles in the Government of the late King's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſhewn that he very well deſerves to be Sainted in the Roman Church, for being ſo Abſolutely and Religiouſly govern'd by You, as became a good and a zealous Roman Catholick: It remains that I venture ſome Advice upon you, according to my Promiſe; which being followed, may preſerve to you the Honour of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accounted a Faithful and Wiſe Guide of a Zealous Roman Catholick Prince's Conſcience to the End.</p>
            <p>And in order to that, I will lay down for a Rule what I ſuppoſe you will readily grant me, <hi>viz.</hi> That you ought to perſwade your <hi>Devoto</hi> always to do that (which, according as Matters ſtand) will moſt tend to the Good and Honour of the Roman Catholick Church. If then I can prove what I adviſe you to, is for the Good and Honour of the Roman Catholick Church, you ought to take my Advice, if you will maintain the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, which you have hitherto had, of acting like an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Man, according to his Principles.</p>
            <p>Not to ſpend many Words about that which ſeems to me a very plain thing: The Advice which I have to give you, is this, To perſwade your <hi>Devoto,</hi> with all ſpeed, to put himſelf into a Monaſtery, and become a <hi>Recluſe.</hi> You may ſay, Yes indeed; juſt ſuch Advice you did
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54828:15"/> expect from an Heretick, that would have the Roman Catholick Cauſe given for loſt in <hi>England,</hi> and would fain peaceaply enjoy his Hereſie: But an Enemies Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is not to be taken; nor he to be believed that ſpeaks for his own Intereſt.</p>
            <p>But pray, think ſeriouſly upon the matter. I do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, That I am ſatisfied in my Conſcience that I am your Friend, and the late KING's Friend, and every Roman Catholick's Friend, in giving you this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: For it is impoſſible you ſhould be ſo ſenſleſs as to think, That you ſhall ever again be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the People of <hi>England,</hi> That a true zealous Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Prince will not deſtroy them, if ever he come to be ſet over them. 'Tis true, they had ſo good (or rather evil) Opinion of your <hi>Devoto,</hi> as to think that his Honour and good Nature would be too ſtrong for his Religion: But ſince he hath ſo abundantly convinced them, That he hath no regard to his Word; no not when he has rais'd Men to the higheſt Truſt in it: That he hath no regard to natural Affection, nor to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity it ſelf, when it ſtands in oppoſition to the Glory of advancing his Religion; but that he values his Religion above all things (as indeed every Man ought to do the true Religion, and he verily believes the Roman Catholick to be the true) there muſt certainly a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Phrenzie ſeize the whole Nation, before ever they will think of taking him again to be their Governour. No; he that is bound in Conſcience to deſtroy Proteſtants, (and we are ſure he will follow his Conſcience herein) can never be a King of Proteſtants; that is, a Preſerver and Defender of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54828:15"/> them: You may as ſoon make a Lion turn a good Herd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the Wolf a good Shepherd, the Fox a good Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Geeſe, as a zealous Papiſt a good King over a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant People. Surely the Frogs, after they had Experience of the Storks Government; and <hi>Jove</hi> had been ſo propitious as once to remove him, though they croaked ſtill as if they in ſome Diſcontent; yet they would never have been ſo mad to have called for their Stork to come and Reign over them again.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Men have always taught the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance, and do not think a Prince for Male-Adminiſtration (to which any Prince may be liable) is to be Dethroned; and therefore they ſtood by King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, to whoſe Charge, at the worſt, nothing could be laid, but ſome particular Acts of Male-Adminiſtration, and who had no Principle that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged him to deſtroy his People, and who ('tis plain) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deſign'd it. But no Proteſtant living can be ſo ſenſleſs, as to think he is not bound to take Protection where he can have it, to defend him from a Prince, who is bound (and will follow his Conſcience) to deſtroy every Man that will continue a Proteſtant: Such a Prince contradicts all the Ends of Government, and is utterly uncapable of it; for no Man can in any Law or Equity, be the Governour of thoſe whom he is bound to Deſtroy, and that as being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary for the Saving his and their Souls. There is no hopes then ever to bring back your <hi>Devoto</hi> into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> unleſs he ſhould turn Proteſtant; which I believe you nor he would agree to, for the gaining of Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Kingdoms. To what purpoſe then will you hazard
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54828:16"/> the Lives of ſo many good Roman Catholicks, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the loſing of the Lands and Stock of the Holy Society, beſides ſo many large Eſtates of Roman Catholicks in <hi>England</hi> (out of which you may continually have good pickings) upon ſuch a loſt Game? 'Tis true, the ſhedding of Hereticks Blood is nothing; but the ſpilling of ſo many good Catholicks Blood as hath been ſpilled already, and is like to be loſt upon ſuch a vain and unlikely attempt, is certainly that which you cannot approve.</p>
            <p>Now all this needleſs expence of Catholick Blood and Treaſure will be ſaved, if you can but perſwade your <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voto</hi> immediately to ſequeſter himſelf from the World, and give himſelf wholly to Contemplation and Devotion, which will compleat the Glory of his Piety, and finiſh the Saint. After that he hath done all that was to be done for the Roman Cathhlick Religion in an active State, What remains for him to do, but to betake himſelf to the Contemplative, which the Roman Church has always taught to be the higheſt State of Perfection upon the Earth? And as in all other matters, ſo in this, be ſure you have no reaſon to doubt of the ready Compliance of your <hi>Devoto;</hi> for he hath already ſhewn an earneſt longing after this State of Perfection; as appeared ſufficiently by his moſt Pious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to Mr. <hi>Chudley,</hi> when he took his leave of him to go to be a <hi>Carthuſian, O God!</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>How much I envy you this Happineſs? And how ſorry am I, that I cannot go with you!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:54828:16"/>
            <p>I do believe therefore, good Father, that in the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of moſt of the Roman Catholick Church, you will be guilty of a very heinous Sin, if you do not promote this moſt earneſt Deſire in this Zealous Prince; for to ſpeak ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to you in the Words of ſome of your greateſt Saints, Will you commit ſo great a Sacriledge as to rob God of one that would give himſelf up wholly to him? Will you rob the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> of ſuch a Princely Husband? Have you no regard to the great Merit of this Prince? And after that he hath done all that was to be done for the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Church, Will you envy him, as a Reward of his Labours in his Old Age, to enjoy the ſweet and happy Eaſe of a Contemplative Life? To ſit down qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, and reflect upon the <hi>Great Things</hi> he hath done and ſuffered for his dear Mother the <hi>Roman Catholick Church;</hi> where he may read at leiſure the Legends of the Roman Saints, and have the comfort to ſee, that his own Deeds have ſurpaſſed all theirs; where he may expect and wait for his own Canonization, the greateſt ſhare of Heaven the Romau Church can give him? Do not therefore, (good Father) as you value your own Credit, or all that in the Romiſh Church is Sacred, as you prize the Lives of Multitudes of Roman Catholicks, as you eſteem their Wealth and Treaſure, and hope to have a ſhare in it; or as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to finiſh the Noble Work, you have hitherto ſo well carried on; and to complete your Saint, or as you fear the dreadful Sin of Sacrilege, do not hinder this Pious and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Deſire of this Zealous Prince, to become a Recluſe, either of the <hi>Carthuſian</hi> Order (according to his own Wiſh) or what other you think moſt convenient for him, according
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54828:17"/> to the Patterns that have been ſet him by ſo many Noble Kings and Princes of your Church.</p>
            <p>Aſſure your ſelf, that by encouraging him in this Deſire, you will purchaſe to your ſelf, and your Order, an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing Merit, endleſs Fame, and perhaps ſome Money be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides: For the Hereticks of <hi>England</hi> are not ſo ill-natured, but that, though they would not have one over them that is bound to kill them, yet to do him any real good, they would (I am perſwaded) afford him a Princely Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, enough to reward you Nobly, and to build a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, whereof he himſelf might be Governour; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this, he may leave enough behind him to pay for his Canonization. Not to mention old Stories of Kings in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, you have two Examples freſh in your Memories of Crowned Heads, that did the ſame thing in different ways; one a Diſciple of Yours, the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> that Reigned 'till he and his Country were utterly weary of one another, and then he wiſely retired, and went into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery. The other, Queen <hi>Chriſtiana</hi> of <hi>Sueden,</hi> who was indeed a wiſe and ſubtle Woman; ſhe being turned of your Religion, plainly ſaw, That a Proteſtant Body could not have a Popiſh Head; and therefore timely compounded for a good Maintenance, and relinquiſh'd. Had you not better then perſwade your Prince to take ſome ſuch Courſe, rather than to ſpend a great deal of precious Catholick Blood and Treaſure? To waſte and wear out his Life in Trouble, and you to get nothing by it? I had thought of other things to Adviſe; but if you take my Advice in this, as all the World knows you may if you will, then there
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54828:17"/> will be no need of any other: But if you will not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed in ſo plain and ſo eaſie a thing as this, To what end ſhould I offer you any other?</p>
            <p>Therefore think of it; and Judge of me as you pleaſe: But in my poor Opinion, I have given you Faithful Advice, and therein ſhewn my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
